A Guide to the Elvin A. Kabat papers FA020
Rockefeller Archive Center
Elvin A. Kabat papers
1934-1990
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Kabat, Elvin A. (Elvin Abraham) (1914-)
FA020
7.25 Cubic Feet 16 document cases
Arrangement note
The Elvin A. Kabat Papers are arranged in two series:
Series 1 - Personal
Series 2 - General Correspondence
Biographical/Historical note
Elvin A. Kabat (1914-2000), a pioneer in the field of immunochemistry, worked for three decades on standardizing immunological science. In the late 1930s he worked as a Fellow at the Institute of Physical Chemistry for the Rockefeller Foundation and later he was a leading member of the faculty at Columbia University. He spent much of his early career working on the structure and immunochemistry of blood-group substances, analyzing the binding properties of antibodies and developing immunodiagnostic tests for multiple sclerosis. He paved the way for the modern experimental autoimmunity process. Kabat also devoted much of his time to mentoring new and often passed-over scientists. He aided foreign medical and chemistry students and provided opportunities to women and African American students in the United States during a time when these opportunities were virtually non-existent.
Through his hard work and endless efforts, a Kabat database was created to aid students in standard immunochemistry. Kabat was also a prolific writer. He authored numerous books, including "Sequences of Proteins of Immunological Interests" and "Kabat and Mayer's Experimental Immunochemistry," which became the text book for all future graduate and doctoral students. He often submitted articles on his latest research and contributed to the Immunochemical Studies on Blood Groups.
Kabat was known for his tireless pursuit of honesty and justice. Through the Freedom of Information Act, Dr. Kabat discovered that during the McCarthy era he was placed on a watch list because of his Eastern European heritage and because of his work with the National Research Council and the United States military.
Elvin A. Kabat (1914-2000), a pioneer in the field of immunochemistry, worked for three decades on standardizing immunological science. In the late 1930s he worked as a Fellow at the Institute of Physical Chemistry for the Rockefeller Foundation and later he was a leading member of the faculty at Columbia University. He spent much of his early career working on the structure and immunochemistry of blood-group substances, analyzing the binding properties of antibodies and developing immunodiagnostic tests for multiple sclerosis. He paved the way for the modern experimental autoimmunity process. Kabat also devoted much of his time to mentoring new and often passed-over scientists. He aided foreign medical and chemistry students and provided opportunities to women and African American students in the United States during a time when these opportunities were virtually non-existent.
Through his hard work and endless efforts, a Kabat database was created to aid students in standard immunochemistry. Kabat was also a prolific writer. He authored numerous books, including "Sequences of Proteins of Immunological Interests" and "Kabat and Mayer's Experimental Immunochemistry," which became the text book for all future graduate and doctoral students. He often submitted articles on his latest research and contributed to the Immunochemical Studies on Blood Groups.
Kabat was known for his tireless pursuit of honesty and justice. Through the Freedom of Information Act, Dr. Kabat discovered that during the McCarthy era he was placed on a watch list because of his Eastern European heritage and because of his work with the National Research Council and the United States military.
Chronology
September 1, 1914 Born in New York City to Harris Kabatchinick, from Lithuania, and Doreen Otesky from the Ukraine.
Spring 1929 Graduated from DeWitt Clinton High School (at the age of 15).
Fall 1929 Began studying at City College.
1932 Obtained a Bachelors of Science degree from the College of the City of New York.
1933-1937 Laboratory Assistant in Immunochemistry, Presbyterian Hospital, New York.
1934 Obtained an MA from Columbia University.
1937 Obtained a Ph.D. from Columbia University.
1937-1938 Rockefeller Foundation Fellow at Institute of Physical Chemistry, Uppsala, Sweden with Professors The Svedberg and Arne Tiselius.
1938-1941 Instructor of Pathology, Cornell Medical College.
1941-1946 Research Associate in Biochemistry (assigned to Neurology), College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University and the Neurological Institute, Presbyterian Hospital.
1942 Married Sally Lennick.
1942-1943 Director of Immunochemical Studies on Meningococcus Meningitis under subcontract from the Meningitis Commission, Board for the Control of Epidemic Diseases, United States Army.
1942-1945 Responsible investigator for three OSRD projects for Committee on Medical Research.
1943-1945 Chemist to an NDRC project. Member, Scientific Staff, Division of War Research, Columbia University.
1945-1947 Consultant, Chemical Warfare Service, Camp Detrick, Maryland.
1946-1948 Assistant Professor of Bacteriology, Columbia University.
1947-1951 Attending Consultant, Veterans Administration Hospital, Kingsbridge, Bronx, New York.
1948-1952 Associate Professor of Bacteriology, Columbia University.
1949 Eli Lilly Award in Bacteriology and Immunology.
1950 Visiting Staff Member, University of California Summer Session, Berkeley, California.
1950-1951 Harvey Lecturer.
1951-1953 Member, Subcommittee on Shock, National Research Council.
1952-1985 Professor of Microbiology, Columbia University.
1953-1967 Member, Medial Advisory Board, National Multiple Sclerosis Society.
1953-1971 Member, Panel on Plasma, National Research Council.
1954-1968 Member, Scientific and Education Council, American Foundation for Allergic Diseases.
1956-1958 Member, Symposium Advisory Committee Unitarian Service Committee.
1956-1959 Member, Research Review Panel, National Multiple Sclerosis Society.
1956-1985 Microbiologist Medical Service, Presbyterian Hospital, Neurological Institute.
1957-1960 Editorial Board Transplantation Bulletin.
1957-1962 Member, Biochemistry Advisory Panel AIBS to Office of Naval Research.
1957-1967 Member, Ad Hoc Panel and Committee on Tissue Transplantation, National Research Council.
1960 William Pyle Philips Lecturer, Haverford College.
1961 Editorial Board, Journal of Immunological.
1961-1964 Councillor American Association of Immunologists.
1962 Golden Hope Chest Award, National Multiple Sclerosis Society.
1962-1968 Scientific Advisory Committee, Institute of Microbiology, Rutgers.
March 1963 Visiting Professor, Department of Microbiology, University of California, San Francisco.
April 1964 Professor, College de France, Paris.
1964 John S. Sharpe Memorial Lecturer, Bryn Mawr Hospital, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania.
1964-1965 Vice President, American Association of Immunologists.
1965 Member of Scientific Committee New York Blood Center.
1965-1966 President, American Association of Immunologists.
1965-1975 Member, World Health Organization Advisory Panel on Immunology.
1966 Member, National Academy of Sciences. Member, American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
1967 Almroth Wright Lecturer, St. Mary's Hospital, Wright Fleming Institute, London.
1968 Claude Bernard Medal, Universit de Montreal. E. B. Wilson Lecturer, University of Texas, Austin.
1968-1972 Chairman, Committee on Latimaria, National Academy of Sciences.
1969 Professor of Human Genetics and Development, Columbia University.
1969-1972 National Science Foundation Panel on Molecular Biology.
1971 Member, Committee on Viral Hepatitis, National Research Council.
1974-1975 Fogarty Scholar at U.S. National Institute of Health (NIH).
1975-2000 Dr. Kabat divided his time between Columbia and NIH.
1991 Received the National Medal of Science.
June 16, 2000 Passed away at the age of 86.
Scope and Contents
This collection is primarily made up of correspondence but also includes biographical information, conference materials, publications, and news releases.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Access is subject to the restrictions specified in the original deed of gift of November 13, 1986, and in the subsequent 2009 deed of gift by LSR's executors. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
File Plan note
Former Classification: XVIII
Biochemistry; Immunology
- Personal, 1934-1988; 1; 0.5 Cubic Feet 1 box
  Arrangement note
  The Personal series is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes Dr. Kabat's curriculum vitae, biographical notes, appointment information, and personal correspondence with colleagues and friends. News releases and lecture series information can also be found here, as well as notes from his sabbatical and correspondence concerning his numerous publications and book information.
  - Appointments, 1974, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Max Berger, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Biographical Sketch, Publication Listings, and Resume
  - Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Publications
  - Elsevier Science Publishers, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, 1934-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fogarty International Center, 1972-1975, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Israel Lecture Conference, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Knickerbocker Blood Bank - Dr. Amos Cohen, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Sabbatical, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Louisa Gross Horwitz Prize, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - News Releases and Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pierre Grabar Conference, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Publications - Book, 1979-1981, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- General Correspondence, 1944-1990; 2; 7.2 Cubic Feet 15 boxes
  The General Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains work-related correspondence between Dr. Kabat and many of his lab assistants and co-workers. This includes information on his work with Michael Heidelberger, Manfred Martin Mayor and notes from Dr. Mayor's memorial speech, notes from the Louisa Gross Horwitz Prize Committee, and letters of gratitude from former students. This section includes files on Dr. Kabat's work on the Matheson Commission, project proposals, and requests for materials, letters of recommendation, critiques, some lab notes, lecture notes, letters from former students and applications from those seeking to study under Dr. Kabat. Awards from various organizations, including the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and various other notifications of awards can also be found in this series, as well as correspondence pertaining to Dr. Kabat's involvement with numerous societies and organizations.
  - Dr. Pradip N. Akolkar, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Howard J. Allen, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Society of Clinical Pathologists - Philip Levine Award, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Byron Anderson - Northwestern University - The Bauman Carbohydrate Binding Prediction Program, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Animals, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Review of Immunology, 1982, 1985, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dr. M. Zoe Atassi, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Statis Aurameas, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (A), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dr. Don A. Baker, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dr. David Baltimore, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dr. Arthur Bank, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dr. Shmuel A. Ben-Sasson, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Dr. Baruj Benacerraf, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dr. Sabhas B. Bhattacharya, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dr. Dietmar G. Braun, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Hagan Bretting, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (Ba-Be), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (Bi-Bu), undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dr. Donald Capra - University of Texas, Dallas, 1976, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dr. Charles Cantor, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Box 5, Folder 52 - Human Genetics and Development
  - Cetus Corporation - Dr. Henry A. Erlich, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dr. Thomas Chalmers, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Dr. Hsu-Tang Chen, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Dr. Shu Chien, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Chinese Society of Hematology - Dr. Che'n Wen-Chieh, 1984, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Dr. John Cisar, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - CODATA Conference, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Columbia University, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Controller's Office - Business Office - Mr. Lee Coyle, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Dr. Audrey Cohen and Dr. Michael Heidelberger, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Cyfoger Certification - Dr. John Rockwell, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence (Ca-Ci), undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence (Cl-Cy), undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Dr. Peter Dmant, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Dr. Keith J. Dorrington, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Dr. Sheldon Dray, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence (D), undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence (E), undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Dr. Ten Feizi, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - French Lecture Series, 1959-1979 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence (F), undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Dr. Rina Ghosh, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Dr. Tarun Kanti Ghosh, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Dr. Irwin Goldstein, 1976-1986 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence (Ga-Gol), undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence (Goo-Gu), undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Dr. Bernard Halpern, 1968-1985 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Dr. Valee Harisdangkul, 1976-1985 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Dr. Beth Hill, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Human Genetics and Development, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Dr. Leroy E. Hood, 1978-1986 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Dr. Tasuku Honjo, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Dr. John H. Humphrey, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence (H), undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Information on the Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Labor, and Health, Education, and Welfare, and Related Agencies, March 1975 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - International Laboratory for Research on Animal Disease, 1975-1981 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Institute for Cancer Research - Dr. Knudson, 1974-1983 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence (I), undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence (J), undated (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Dr. Akira Kobata, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Dr. Karen Krupen, 1981-1990 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence (Ka-Ke), undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence (Ki-Ku), undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Dr. Sung La, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Dr. Eric Cheong Hon Lai, 1982-1987 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Dr. James W. Larrick, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Cetus Immune Research Lab
  - Dr. Raymond Lemieux, 1975-1980 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Dr. Raymond Lemieux, 1981-1987 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Dr. Richard A. Lerner, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Dr. Kenneth Lloyd, 1975-1987 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Louisa Gross Horwitz Prize Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence (L), undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Dr. S. Daniel Makover, 1984-1988 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Dr. Donald M. Marcus, 1975-1984 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Dr. Michael N. Margolies, 1977-1984 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Dr. Paul A. Marks, 1976-1980 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Matheson Commission - Correspondence and Reports, 1944-1962 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Matheson Commission - Correspondence and Reports, 1963-1978, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Dr. Tsudasa Matsuda, 1983-1988 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Dr. Linda Matsuuchi, 1980-1984 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Dr. Manfred Martin Mayor, 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Dr. Manfred Martin Mayor - Obituary and Memorial Material, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Dr. Florence M. McAuliffe, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Dr. Vincent J. McAuliffe, 1983-1986 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Dr. Esther L. McCandless, 1979-1982 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Dr. Hugh O'Neill McDevitt, 1979-1983 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Allyn McIntyre - Journal of Theoretical Biology, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Dr. Ian McIntyre, 1975-1986 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Dr. Giampaolo Merlini, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Microbiology, 1976-1984 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Dr. Cesar Milestein, 1978-1986 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Dr. Carlos Moreno, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Dr. Richard Y. Morita, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Dr. Sherie Morrison, 1981-1986 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence (M), undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - National Academy of Science, 1977-1984 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - The National Multiple Sclerosis Society, undated (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Dr. Lenore Neigeborn, October 27, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - New York Blood Center, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Dr. Barbara Newman, 1980-1987 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Dr. Walter Newman, 1977-1983 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Dr. Yutaka Nishioka, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Nobel Prize Committee, 1981-1985 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Correspondence (N), undated (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Dr. Susuma Ohno, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Dr. Elliot Osserman, 1978-1985 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Correspondence (O), undated (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Dr. Eduardo Paldan, 1976-1986 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Dr. Miercio Pereia, 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Dr. Jerzy Petryniak, 1975-1984 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Dr. Ronald D. Poretz, 1978-1983 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Correspondence (Pa-Ph), undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Correspondence (Pi-Py), undated (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Quarterly Review of Biology, 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Mr. James Quirk, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Radiation Safety - Correspondence and Agreements, 1977-1984 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Dr. Arepalli S. Rao, 1979-1984 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Dr. Dieter Roelcke, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Dr. Noel R. Rose, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Dr. Jonathan Rothbard, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Dr. Luciana Rouis, 1975-1982 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Correspondence (Ra-Ri), undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Correspondence (Ro-Ru), undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Dr. Manju Sarkar, 1975-1984 (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Dr. Conrad Schuerch, 1978-1983 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Dr. Stuart Schlossman, 1977-1987 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Dr. Robert Schwartz, 1983-1988 (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Dr. Fred Seymour, 1977-1982 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Dr. Jacqueline Sharon, 1980-1985 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Dr. Nathan Sharon, 1975-1985 (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Dr. Santosh Kumar Sikdar, 1981-1985 (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Arthur M. Silverstein - "History of Immunology", 1982-1985 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Dr. Alan Solomon, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Soviet Union, 1975, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - Dr. Georg Springer, 1964-1988 (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Dr. Lisa Steiner, 1978-1987 (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Dr. B. David Stollar, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Dr. Jack L. Strominger, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - Dr. Shunji Sugii, 1976-1988 (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Dr. Lanping Amy Sung, 1978-1988 (Box 14, Folder 143)
  - Correspondence (Sa-Sh), undated (Box 14, Folder 144)
  - Correspondence (Si-Sz), undated (Box 14, Folder 145)
  - Dean Donald Tapley, 1976-1981 (Box 14, Folder 146)
  - Dr. Mitsuo Torii, 1975-1988 (Box 14, Folder 147)
  - Trends in Biomedical Sciences, 1975-1983 (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - Dr. Nancy A. Treptow, 1982-1987 (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Correspondence (T), undated (Box 15, Folder 150)
  - Correspondence (U), undated (Box 15, Folder 151)
  - Dr. Giuseppe Vicari, 1966-1970 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Correspondence (V), undated (Box 15, Folder 153)
  - Dr. Irving Weissman, 1976-1980 (Box 15, Folder 154)
  - The Weizmann Institute of Science, 1975-1984 (Box 15, Folder 155)
  - Dr. Jeffery L. Winkelhake, 1976-1981 (Box 15, Folder 156)
  - Dr. Charles Wood, 1980-1985 (Box 15, Folder 157)
  - World Health Organization, 1976-1985 (Box 15, Folder 158)
  - Dr. Albert Ming-Tao Wu, 1975-1984 (Box 16, Folder 159)
  - Dr. Albert Ming-Tao Wu, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 160)
  - Correspondence (Wa-Wh), undated (Box 16, Folder 161)
  - Correspondence (Wi-Wy), undated (Box 16, Folder 162)
  - Correspondence (Y), undated (Box 16, Folder 163)
  - Correspondence (Z), undated (Box 16, Folder 164)